A Guide to the Nancy O'Brien Papers
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Nancy O'Brien Papers
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
14815
ca. 4000 items
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions
Acquisitions
The papers were a gift to the University of Virginia Library from Nancy O'Brien on August 31, 2009.
Biographical/Historical Information
Nancy Kilpatrick O'Brien was born in Newark, New Jersey in 1936. From 1954-1957 she attended Massachusetts General Hospital School of Nursing earning her nursing degree. She became active in politics at age thirty-nine when she moved to Charlottesville because her husband, Dr. William O'Brien accepted a position in Internal Medicine at the University of Virginia. She joined the Women's League of Voters and was appointed Treasurer of the Thomas Jefferson Planning District Commission by City Council in 1973-1974, and Chairman in 1974. She ran for City Council and was elected first woman mayor of Charlottesville in 1976. She also served on many community organizations including the Jefferson School Task Force, the Community Development Task Force, the Advisory Committee on the South Rivanna Reservoir study and many housing committees. She also worked as a facilitator to improve the services of many community service organizations. Early in her political career she met Francis Fife, a former mayor of Charlottesville (1972-1974) who later became her second husband. She has four children.
Scope and Content
The papers of Mayor Nancy O'Brien contain correspondence, political campaign information, and topical files regarding many issues that were facing the city of Charlottesville, Virginia from 1973 to 1981; [1982-2008]. The correspondence includes general correspondence, letters to the Mayor about routine issues, and congratulations from political figures such as Charles S. Robb, Thomas J. Michie, Tim Kaine, J. Kenneth Robinson, and Mark Warner. The political files include information about upcoming primaries. The topical files reflect O'Brien's interest in the community with a particular focus on the development of strong neighborhood communities, economic development, city annexation, city planning, housing, and local transportation issues. The collection contains ca. 4000 items and 22 Hollinger boxes which make up 9 linear feet.
Specific economic issues mentioned are the construction and revitalization plan of the Downtown Mall, the decision to construct the Fashion Square Mall, plans for the Vinegar Hill area ten years after it had been destroyed and then left abandoned, and the designation of Fifeville as a historic neighborhood. There are also Charlottesville Albemarle Transportation Studies on the Meadowcreek Parkway, and extension of McIntire Road, Schenks Branch, and Preston Avenue. Other events mentioned are Queen Elizabeth's visit to Charlottesville for the bicentennial, racial diversity, and a sister cities program.
There are also minutes and correspondence from City Council and strategies for sharing services between the City and the County. There are similarly joint committees between the City and the University of Virginia. Of particular interest regarding the University is a photocopy of a letter written by Thomas Jefferson about the opening of the University of Virginia.
There are also student papers from 1983-1986 when O'Brien obtained a Masters degree in Public Administration at the University of Virginia (after being Mayor). There are also papers from when O'Brien taught planning courses (on Fifeville) at the University. There is a copy of her thesis (and thesis research) on Planning District Commissions in Virginia. (Series II UVA Graduate Student and Professor) There are also papers from her work as executive director of the Thomas Jefferson Planning Commission [1979-2006] (Series III TJPDC) and papers from her private work in which she acted as a facilitator for agencies that served the needs of the community. (Series V Facilitator) There are a few papers from her work with the Housing Authority.
There are also minutes from the Jefferson School Task Force which was appointed by City Council to preserve Jefferson School as a historical institution. Included is information about grant funding (Bama funds from the Dave Mathews Band) and information about the history of Jefferson School and early African American life in Charlottesville. There are copies of photographs from the Rufus Holsinger collection. (Series IV Jefferson School)
There is information on racial diversity from a group titled, "Many Races, One Community" which was organized by Nancy O'Brien to address racial tensions. These tensions had arisen in 2002 following an occurrence of violence by several African American Charlottesville High School students against white University of Virginia students. "Many Races, One Community" planned events in an attempt to unite people from different cultural experiences. (Series I Mayor and City Council topical files: Race)
There are also speeches of Nancy O'Brien from 1971 to 2008 including when she was mayor (Series VI Speeches) and awards, certificates, and a scrapbook of newspaper clippings and photographs (Series VII)
Arrangement
The collection is organized into seven series, Series I Mayor of Charlottesville and city council member A. Correspondence files B. Political files C. Topical files; Series II UVA classes A. Graduate student B. Professor; Series III Thomas Jefferson District Planning Commission; Series IV Jefferson School; Series V Facilitator; Series VI Speeches, and Series VII Scrapbook pages, photographs, awards, certificates, and trophies
Contents Listing
- Series I: Mayor of Charlottesville and City Council Member
  - A. Correspondence Files
    - 1976 General Correspondence, 70 items (Box-folder 1:1)
      Constituents and colleagues correspond about a variety of issues pertaining to Charlottesville including drainage problems on Meade Avenue, parking tickets, street improvements, preservation of the Fifeville neighborhood, danger and confusion due to duplicate street names, fasting and prayer day, lights and pedestrian safety near the hospital, girls attention home, twin sister city in Italy, policing of Wertland Street, school invitations, and resignations
    - 1977-1980; 1992 General Correspondence, 58 items (Box-folder 1:2)
      Constituents and colleagues correspond about a variety of issues pertaining to Charlottesville including parking tickets, sidewalks on Old Lynchburg Road and Jefferson Park Avenue, WVPT month, advertisement for convention bureaus, separation of the chamber of commerce from local governments, law week, tennis week, regional jails, attrition of jobs, Charlottesville High School gymnasium, invitations, resignations, and thank you letters. There is a tribute to Bill Elwood. There is also a hate letter addressed to Nancy O'Brien.
    - 1978-1980 General Correspondence from children, 103 items (Box-folder 1:3)
      There are letters to the Mayor from school children
    - 1976 July-September Mayor correspondence, 53 items (Box-folder 1:4)
      Letters are organized alphabetically by their original authors, Abernathy-Woodson. Topics include a park off Calhoun Street, a song about Charlottesville, inclusion of more Council members, paving the Charlottesville High School Parking Lot, Community Attention Home Board, DMV use of Wilder Road, Trainees for Rivanna Water and Sewer, a limit on sewer connections, business education class, Youth Employment Service year round, letter of support for Bob Wenger, McGuffey artist space, resignations and appointments, invitations to speak at Alpha Kappa Alpha Sorority, and the Bayly Museum and other concerns from community leaders, parents, businessman and citizens. Included is a handwritten statement by Francis Fife nominating Nancy O'Brien for mayor.
    - 1976 October-December Mayor correspondence, 23 items (Box-folder 1:5)
      Letters are organized alphabetically by their authors, Black-Wiley Topics include noise control, list of task force members on the Social Development Commission, industrial development, student city council, paving of Charlottesville High School Parking Lot, Federal and State Library Funds, Community Attention Home for Girls, visit to the Joint Security Complex, Senator James Harry Michael dinner, and resignation of George Wiley from the Planning Commission and other concerns from community leaders, parents, businessman and citizens.
    - 1977 January-April Mayor correspondence, 36 items (Box-folder 1:6)
      Letters are organized alphabetically by their authors, Berman-Williams There is a letter of protest from Mayor O'Brien against the Criminal Justice Planner making public comments about police salaries. Other topics include tax abatement for rehabilitative housing, a workshop on low income housing, economic development, energy conservation, Virginia State Federation of Colored Women's Club Convention in Charlottesville, Sunset Club for senior citizens asking for help with meals, public service corporations to pay taxes, Charlottesville Albemarle Planning Committee for a Cultural Center, invitation to speak to the Delegates at the 43 rd Annual Grand Communication, invitation to welcome the Municipal Electric Power Association, Bicentennial commission donation of emergency fuel to the city, coat of arms for the city, bicycle paths, a reference for Doug Venable and various resignations, and other concerns from community leaders, parents, businessman and citizens.
    - 1977 May—November Mayor Correspondence, 41 items (Box-folder 1:7)
      Alphabetical: Arnett-Williams Selection of Architects for Library/Post Office renovation (includes correspondence into 1978), McGuffey bid, invitation to speak to the American association of Retired Persons Area Council, funding for additional youth programs, Housing Authority on the Garrett Street Project, Housing Authority to report to City Council, developing a plan with the county for fuel distribution, zoning ordinance, Jefferson Cable, "Dick Gilliam Day," Virginia Council on Health and Medical Care asked for funding, State Air Control Pollution Board, testimony delivered about the Rape Crisis Group, teacher of the year recommendation, Chamber of Commerce was unable to support the Convention Bureau Activities, Virginia National Bank loan to the Housing Authority, resignations and other concerns from community leaders, parents, businessman and citizens.
    - 1978 Mayor Correspondence, 60 items (Box-folder 2:1)
      Alphabetical: Aaron-Wood
      Some topics include: The Perry Foundation gave sixty thousand dollars to the city to construct tennis courts at Pen Park, cooperation with the Chamber of Commerce, failure of attrition program, Schenk's Branch Project, school transportation for the hearing impaired (Aaron Farley,) drainage problems on Chesapeake Street, Charlottesville Development Group, Charlottesville Retail Association, "Keep America Beautiful" Campaign, Rivanna Water and Sewer Authority to place a screen over pipes, housing efforts for the handicapped, resignations, appointments, thank you notes for community service, parking for Martha Jefferson Hospital, fuel relief program, sign ordinances, lighting, tax issues, city planning survey, and other concerns from community leaders, parents, businessman and citizens.
    - 1977-1978 General Correspondence Memos of City Council, 20 items (Box-folder 2:2)
      There are memos about the gas rate case, coat of arms, library budget, architects for the library, Virginia Municipal League tour, Conservation Council of Virginia grant for Ivy Creek Natural Area, Centel Board of Directors, donation of "mini-park," railroad plans in the state, bridge on Park Street extended, and legality of the CHIP Program
    - 1976-1978 General Correspondence Neighborhood Meetings about Budget, 44 items (Box-folder 2:3)
      List of neighborhood presidents, capital improvements, newsletters, City Council memos about neighborhood meetings and budget, notes by Nancy O'Brien for a public service announcement encouraging attendance at the meeting, and instructions and invitation to a budget game.
    - 1976-1978; 2002-2005 General correspondence Neighborhood Meetings, 39 items (Box-folder 2:4)
      Included is correspondence about neighborhood communities such as, Rose Hill, Jefferson Park Avenue, Ridge Street, Greenbrier, Belmont, Fifeville, and Venable
    - 1977-1978; 1980; 1998; 1999 General Correspondence thank you letters to Nancy O'Brien, 9 items (Box-folder 2:5)
      Correspondents include Eugene German, Peggy King, Donna P. Massey, Bessie E. Avent, Agnes W. Sullivan, Opal D. David, Thomas B. Leitch, Roger C. Wiley, and Robert Gilmore
    - 1976-1986 Personal correspondence Nancy O'Brien, 20 items (Box-folder 2:6)
      There are letters from the community about her hair styles, congratulations on receiving her master's degree, thanks for giving a memorial speech at the funeral of Marcia Mashaw, and congratulations on obtaining the position, Executive Director of the Thomas Jefferson Planning Commission. Correspondents include H. Bernhard Ewert II, Carol E. Haberly, Priscilla Whiting, Francis Fife, Carl and MaryJo Ayers, Alice Howard, Mario Cazzamiga, and Opal E. David.
    - VIP Correspondence (alphabetical by name of VIP)
      - 1976 August 3 Nancy O'Brien letter to Senator Harry F. Byrd, 3 items (Box-folder 2:7)
        O'Brien wrote letters asking him to support the general revenue sharing bill.
      - 2002 May-June Nancy O'Brien letter to John Casteen, 2 items (Box-folder 2:8)
        The letter is a response to a form letter sent by the University asking her (as an Alumnus) for donations to the University. Nancy O'Brien responded directly to President Casteen that since the University did not consider their own impact on the community or on their own poorly paid staff, she would use her funds to help the community instead of the University.
      - 1977 October 6 Nancy O'Brien letter to Governor Mills E. Godwin, 2 items (Box-folder 2:9)
        Nancy O'Brien asked the Governor to declare Charlottesville a drought emergency and grant the City authority to enact mandatory water conservation ordinances
      - 1978 February Nancy O'Brien letter and Frank Hereford, 2 items (Box-folder 2:10)
        President Hereford wrote to Nancy O'Brien recommending Dennis Barnes to serve as the University representative at the Charlottesville Development Group and Nancy O'Brien thanked him.
      - 2003 July 25 Tim Kaine to Nancy O'Brien, 1 item (Box-folder 2:11)
        He wrote that he enjoyed visiting Nancy and Francis Fife last week
      - 1976 March 3 Thomas J. Michie, Jr. to Nancy O'Brien, 1 item (Box-folder 2:12)
        Michie congratulated O'Brien on winning the Democratic nomination for City Council
      - 1976 July 6 Charles S. Robb to Nancy O'Brien, 1 item (Box-folder 2:13)
        Charles Robb wrote that he enjoyed meeting her and mentioned that her office is off to a great start with meeting the Queen of England and the President of the United States. He wrote, "What are you going to do for an encore?"
      - 1977 January 4 Nancy O'Brien letter to Charles S. Robb, 2 items (Box-folder 2:14)
        Nancy O'Brien wrote a letter to Mr. Robb wishing him well in his campaign for Lieutenant Governor. There is also a letter from the Secretary of the Commonwealth notifying Nancy that she would not be appointed on the State Board of Community Colleges.
      - 1977 March 15 J. Kenneth Robinson to Nancy O'Brien, 1 item (Box-folder 2:15)
        Congressman Robinson wrote Nancy O'Brien that he would be supportive of H.R. 1522.
      - 2002 August 5 Governor Mark Warner to Nancy O'Brien, 4 items (Box-folder 2:16)
        Governor Warner thanked Nancy for her help in recommending Al Weed to be appointed member of the Virginia Land Conservation Foundation Board of Trustees
  - B. Political Files
    - 1976 City Council Elections Nancy O'Brien, 115 items (Box-folder 2:17)
      H. Lane Kneedler and Nancy O'Brien ran for City Council. Also running for the three seats were Frank Tomlin, Sherman R. White, Robert W. Stroh, Norman Lushbaugh, Ed Gatewood, and Laurence Brunton. Included are resumes for Nancy O'Brien and H. Lane Kneedler. There are news clippings, campaign flyers, and statements about political beliefs and policies. There are also letters of congratulations to Nancy O'Brien including one from Mrs. Edgar F. Shannon.
    - 1978 City Council Elections Thomas Albro and Frank Buck, 11 items (Box-folder 2:18)
      There is a statement by Francis Fife announcing that he would not be seeking reelection for City Council Member. There are newspaper clippings and editorials about the campaign in which Frank Buck and Thomas Albro were elected and James Hicks lost.
    - 2002 City Council Election Blake Caravati and Alexandra Searls for City Council, 75 items (Box-folder 2:19)
      The e-mails are critical of Alexandra Searls. There are campaign flyers, editorials, newspaper clippings, and e-mails about issues and strategies in the City Council election in which Rob Schilling won the Council Seat in an upset over Alexandra Searls. The e-mails include vivid descriptions of other politicians and officials (including Waldo Jaquith, Joan Fenton, and David Simmons) in the Charlottesville community. Also included are e-mails from the democrats about debriefing of the election and making plans for Meredith Richards campaign.
    - 2004 City Council Elections David Brown, 1 item (Box-folder 2:20)
      There is an editorial to the Daily Progress from Nancy O'Brien declaring her support for David Brown, Kendra Hamilton and Kevin Lynch
    - 1984 Congress Election Francis Fife, 35 items (Box-folder 3:1)
      Francis Fife ran for the 7 th District Democratic nomination for Congress. Included are campaign literature, flyers, and photographs of press conferences.
    - 2001 County Supervisor Election Connie Brennan, 12 items (Box-folder 3:2)
      There are newspaper clippings about the election for east and central seats on the Nelson County Board of Supervisors in which Connie Brennan and Gary Wood were running against Bob Rose, and R. Carlton Ballowe
    - 2001 State Senate Special Election Emily Couric seat, 38 items (Box-folder 3:3)
      There are news clippings about Nancy O'Brien running in a special election to fill the 25 th District Senate seat (Emily Couric's seat) along with Meredith Richards, Blake Caravati, David Toscani, Susan Payne, Al Weed, and Creigh Deeds. There is also correspondence and campaign literature.
    - 2002 Congress Election Meredith Richards, 70 items (Box-folder 3:4)
      There are descriptions of how to organize the campaign for Richards in the 5 th Congressional District against Virgil Goode, including information about results of their debate, map of voting precincts, Democratic Committee lists, handwritten notes about campaign strategies by Nancy O'Brien, calendar of Meredith Richards events, and e-mail messages between David Simmons, Tina, Reese, Valerie L'Herrou, Brian Wheeler, Cheryl Oliver, Parthy Monagan, Lloyd Snook, Will Harvey, Nancy O'Brien, and Alexandra Searls
    - 2004 Congress Election Al Weed, 45 items (Box-folder 3:5)
      There are e-mails, flyers, and notes about Al Weed's campaign.
    - 2001-2003 Democratic Party, 21 items (Box-folder 3:6)
      Statement of democratic principles, By-laws of the Charlottesville Democratic Committee, maps of voting precincts, donation lists, e-mails between Russell Perry, Kevin Lynch, David Repass, Lloyd Snook, Valerie l'Herrou, Felice Boling-Key, Alexandra Searls, and Waldo Jaquith. There are handwritten notes by Nancy O'Brien. Photographs from fundraising events
  - C. Topical Files
    - 1977 Affirmative Action, 2 items (Box-folder 3:7)
      Included is a memo from City Manager, Cole Hendrix to W. P. Mitchell on recruitment activities and notes written by Nancy O'Brien
    - 1971; 1979 Annexation, 35 items (Box-folder 3:8)
      There are memos and letters about the county usage of city utilities, Bill Number 328, and the tensions between city and county annexation law suits. Also included are ordinances, resolutions, a typescript of a radio broadcast, and newspaper clippings (including a map of city county boundaries). There are also clippings and maps about annexation and legislation proposed by Thomas J. Michie Jr.
    - 1975; 2003 Piedmont Council for the Arts, 6 items (Box-folder 3:9)
      There is a newspaper clipping about converting McGuffey School into a community arts and crafts center. There is also a nomination for Helen B. (Sandy) Snook for the PCA Arts award for 2003.
    - 1971-1978 Administrative Files: Budget, 44 items (Box-folder 3:10)
      There are memos, notes, and newspaper clippings pertaining to the local and state budget
    - 1974-1981 Charlottesville Area Transportation Study (CATS), 39 items (Box-folder 3:11)
      There are correspondence, newspaper clippings, and minutes of the Policy and Technical Committee for the Charlottesville Area Transportation Restudy. There is information about speed limits, road improvements, bypass routes, roads, and highways in Charlottesville and Albemarle County including Route 29, 250, McIntire Road, Hydraulic Road, and Michie Drive.
    - 1977; 1978-1979 City-County Joint Activities, 24 items (Box-folder 4:1)
      There is a proposal to Albemarle County from the City of Charlottesville recommending that they form a community with common interests. There is correspondence between Board of Supervisors, Gerald Fisher and Mayor Laurence Brunton and a statement to the Board of Supervisors about negotiations to avoid annexation and encourage revenue sharing. Also included is a Summary of Joint Activities
    - 1980 City-County Joint Activities, 51 items (Box-folder 4:2)
    - 1978 City Council, 50 items (Box-folder 4:3)
      City Manager, Cole Hendrix set up a Council Retreat to study the priorities and needs of the city in the future. There is a list of possible income sources estimated for five years ahead. There are also newspaper clippings regarding office locations for the City and a new representative for the Belmont Neighborhood and other city council agendas
    - 1976-1977 City Planning Commission Minutes, 7 items (Box-folder 4:4)
      The minutes from January 11, 1977 mentioned the request for a zoning change at University Circle; drainage problem from Hydraulic Road as well as other zoning changes and road concerns.
    - 1976 -1980 City of Charlottesville and the University of Virginia, 26 items (Box-folder 4:5)
      There are newspaper clippings and a copy of The University Register (Nov. 15, 1976 vol. 6, no. 21) There is correspondence from Cole Hendrix, UVA President, Frank Hereford, Nancy O'Brien and the Jefferson Park Avenue Neighborhood Association about communicating more directly with each other so that there would be less confusion about statements attributed to them in the media. There is also a memo about establishing a "Fraternity Committee" For document about the opening of the University of Virginia by Thomas Jefferson (photocopy) see University of Virginia
    - 1995 Cole Hendrix, 1 item (Box-folder 4:6)
      Tribute to Cole Hendrix
    - 1974-1975 Disaster Preparedness, 5 items (Box-folder 4:7)
      There are newspaper clippings about a flood plan notes by Nancy O'Brien
    - 1976-1977 Economic Development Commission, 80 items (Box-folder 4:8)